Guide to the Vladimir and Véra Nabokov publishing correspondence, 1945-1977.
Nabokov, Vladimir and Véra publishing correspondence, 1945-1977
Division of Rare and Manuscript Collections, Cornell University Library
Vladimir and Véra Nabokov publishing correspondence, 1945-1977.
4627
Vladimir Vladimirovich Nabokov, 1899-1977.
ca. 2,500 items
Correspondence.
Division of Rare and Manuscript Collections, Cornell University Library
Correspondence of Vladimir Nabokov, his literary agents, and his publishers regarding publication of his works, as well as related correspondence of Véra Nabokov.
COLLECTION DESCRIPTION
Approximately 100 original letters and telegrams between Vladimir Nabokov and Doussia Ergaz and Marie Schébéko, his agents at Bureau Litteraire D. Clairouin, discussing in detail rights and translations, Lolita, and other professional matters; approximately 325 items between Maurice Girodias at The Olympia Press and Ergaz and Schébéko, discussing publication of Lolita, in English and in translations; the French ban on the novel; and subjects related to the early life of the book; approximately 2000 items capturing three decades of correspondence between Véra and those involved with the publication of Nabokov's works. Including about 500 typed letters signed by Véra Nabokov to Ergaz and Schébéko as well as carbons of their replies, and related correspondence and documents.
SUBJECTS
Names:
Nabokov, Vladimir Vladimirovich, 1899-1977.; Doussia, Ergaz.; Girodias, Maurice.; Nabokov, Véra, 1902-1991.; Schébéko, Marie.; Bureau Litteraire D. Clairouin.; Cornell University--Faculty.; Olympia Press (Paris, France).
Subjects:
Authors and publishers.; Censorship--Law and legislation--United States.; Publishers and publishing--France.; Publishers and publishing--United States.
INFORMATION FOR USERS
SERIES LIST
Series I. Outgoing Correspondence from Vladimir Nabokov 1947-1975
Box 1: 1947-1958
Box 2: 1959-1975
Series II. Lolita Correspondence between Olympia Press, Clairouin, and Vladimir Nabokov
Box 3
Series III. Lolita Miscellaneous 1945-1970 (Correspondence, Statements, Publicity, Contracts, Legal Documents)
Box 4
Series IV.: Outgoing Correspondence from Véra Nabokov 1949-1977
Box 5 1949-1966
Box 6 1966-1977
Series V. Correspondence to and from Clairouin 1947-1977
Box 7 1947-1964
Box 8 1964-1977
Box 9 1959 (includes contracts and calculations)
Series VI. Miscellaneous 1932-1976 (Correspondence, Publicity, Contracts, Statements)
Box 10
CONTAINER LIST
- Series I. Outgoing Correspondence from Vladimir Nabokov 1947-1975
  - TLS to Madame D. Ergaz from Vladimir Nabokov, June 3, 1947. (Box 1, Folder 1)
    Written from Craigie Circle, Cambridge MA, in French, concerning translation, publication, and cinema rights for Laughter in the Dark, Invitation to a Beheading, and The Defense, as well as money owed VN by various sources. Lightly annotated.
  - TLS to Madame D. Ergaz from Vladimir Nabokov, August 9, 1947. (Box 1, Folder 2)
    Written from Columbine Lodge, Estes Park, CO, in French, concerning the contract for the French translation and publication of Gogol, with brief mention of contract negotiations involving Invitation, The Defense, and VN's short stories.
  - TLS to Madame D. Ergaz (Ida Mikhailovna) from Vladimir Nabokov, November 14, 1947. (Box 1, Folder 3)
    Written from Craigie Circle, Cambridge MA, in French, inquiring after the status of contract negotiations for the French publication of Gogol, The Defense, and Invitation, and requesting an additional copy of a newly translated short story after the first copy had apparently been lost in the mail.
  - TLS to Madame D. Ergaz from Vladimir Nabokov, postmarked January 18, 1948. (Box 1, Folder 4)
    Written from Craigie Circle, Cambridge MA, in French, expressing dissatisfaction with the French translation of an unidentified short story, and, while giving consent to its publication in magazine form, suggesting Jarl Priel for future translation projects. Asks whether Ergaz has found a French publisher for Joueur, and gives news of the American publication of Nine Stories, and the British edition of Gogol. Asks for news of Ergaz, especially concerning the publication of her book, and wishes his agent a happy new year.
  - TLS to Madame D. Ergaz from Vladimir Nabokov, May 29, 1949. (Box 1, Folder 5)
    Written from 802 E. Seneca Street, Ithaca NY, in French, concerning a contract with Albin Michel, informing Ergaz of the Nabokovs' summer plans and the resultant need for the contract to be signed by June 20, as well as thanking Ergaz for her efforts on behalf of Sebastian Knight.
  - TLS to Madame D. Ergaz from Vladimir Nabokov, June 20, 1949. (Box 1, Folder 6)
    Written from 802 E. Seneca Street, Ithaca NY, in French, concerning changes to a contract (probably Sebastian Knight), and specifying summer addresses.
  - TLS to Madame D. Ergaz from Vladimir Nabokov, July 12, 1949. (Box 1, Folder 7)
    Addressed from 802 E. Seneca Street, Ithaca NY, but apparently written from Salt Lake City, in French, referring to 2 copies of a contract signed by VN and by the American editor of Sebastian Knight, James Laughlin of New Directions, enclosed with the letter.
  - TLS to Madame D. Ergaz from Vladimir Nabokov, May 15, 1950. (Box 1, Folder 8)
    Written from 802 E. Seneca Street, Ithaca NY, in French, opening with a series of questions about the publication status of Sebastian Knight, then asking Ergaz to obtain for VN two copies of The Defense ("par moi"), and informing Ergaz that a book of memoirs (Conclusive Evidence/Speak, Memory) is to be published by Harper the following spring.
  - TLS to Madame D. Ergaz from Vladimir Nabokov, August 16, 1950. (Box 1, Folder 9)
    Written from 802 E. Seneca Street, Ithaca NY, in French, expressing "despair" over the first six chapters of a translation by Davet, who, VN claims, while possessed of good intentions and an intelligent way of reading, does not comprehend English, and employs a cliché-ridden French. He asks Ergaz for her thoughts on this matter, and insists that he must be allowed to correct the proofs. He mentions again the upcoming publication of his memoirs.
  - TLS to Madame D. Ergaz from Vladimir Nabokov, September 4, 1950. (Box 1, Folder 10)
    An anxious letter, written from 802 E. Seneca Street, Ithaca NY, in French, concerning the whereabouts of the manuscript translation of Invitation, and Ergaz's reception of his letter regarding the Sebastian Knight translation, both of which things VN has just heard about from Mme. Davet.
  - TL to Madame D. Ergaz from Vladimir Nabokov, November 12, 1950. (Box 1, Folder 11)
    In French, regarding the many faults of Davet's translation of Sebastian Knight. VN has eliminated all of Davet's "Prussianisms" while moaning in distress over each line.
  - TLS to Madame D. Ergaz from Vladimir Nabokov, December 1, 1950. (Box 1, Folder 12)
    Written from 802 E. Seneca Street, Ithaca NY, in French, informing Ergaz that he has sent her the corrected manuscript of Sebastian translation, promising to write Davet a friendly note, and initiating the quest to find Conclusive Evidence a French publisher; urges that the translation of Conclusive Evidence be passed to Priel.
  - TLS to Madame D. Ergaz from Vladimir Nabokov, March 19, 1951. (Box 1, Folder 13)
    Written from 802 E. Seneca Street, Ithaca NY, in French, inquiring after various works ( Conclusive Evidence, The Defense, Despair) in various states of (French) publication, and commenting on Yvonne Davet's probable reaction to Gide's death.
  - TLS to Madame D. Ergaz from Vladimir Nabokov, August 15, 1951. (Box 1, Folder 14)
    Addressed from 623 Highland Road, Ithaca NY, but probably written from "les 'wilds' de l'Ouest", in French, treats the inadequacy of Yvonne Davet as translator of Sebastian, and urges that she not be hired to translate his autobiography as, counter to VN's own aesthetic search for the new, Davet (claims VN) relies on language devalued by over-use. Some discussion (from memory) of the film rights for Chambre Noir (Laughter in the Dark). Includes description of Nabokovs' difficult financial situation.
  - TLS to Madame D. Ergaz from Vladimir Nabokov, October 30, 1951. (Box 1, Folder 15)
    Written from 623 Highland Road, Ithaca NY, in French, discussing the selection and order of novels both English and Russian should Ergaz succeed in arranging with a major French publishing house to publish all of VN's work. VN wishes to omit his Russian novels Mary, King Queen Knave, and Podvig on the grounds of their poor quality and his practice of borrowing material from these Russian texts when writing in English.
  - TLS to Madame D. Ergaz from Vladimir Nabokov, November 28, 1951. (Box 1, Folder 16)
    Written from 623 Highland Road, Ithaca NY, in French, concerning the contract with La Table Rond to publish a number of his works.
  - TL to Monsieur Brice Parain (Editions Gallimard) from Vladimir Nabokov, April 2, 1952. (Box 1, Folder 17)
    Written from 9 Maynard Place, Cambridge MA, in French, requesting notice of Gallimard's intentions regarding two works ( Bend Sinister and Conclusive Evidence) so that VN may know whether he is free to offer rights to other editors.
  - TLS to Madame D. Ergaz from Véra Nabokov, with autographed handwritten note from Vladimir Nabokov, August 12, 1952. (Box 1, Folder 18)
    Written from Afton, WO, in French, hoping that Ergaz was able to alter the contract with Table Rond as desired, and thanking the agent for her patience she has shown and the trouble she has taken. Both Vera and her husband hope that the translation of Gogol will prove satisfactory. Autographed note from VN reiterating that he must see Gogol translation before it goes to printers.
  - TLS to Madame D. Ergaz from Vladimir Nabokov, September 30, 1952. (Box 1, Folder 19)
    Written on letterhead from the Department of Russian Literature, Goldwin Smith Hall, Cornell University, Ithaca NY, in French, concerning translation issues in The Gift and Conclusive Evidence. VN complains that while Marcelle Sibon's French is excellent, her English is insufficient. He apologizes for seeming difficult, but insists that the question of style is of extreme importance.
  - TLS to Madame D. Ergaz from Vladimir Nabokov, December 29, 1952. (Box 1, Folder 20)
    Written from Goldwin Smith Hall, Ithaca NY, in French, concerning translation issues in Conclusive Evidence and Invitation, and wishing Ergaz a happy new year.
  - TLS to Madame D. Ergaz from Vladimir Nabokov, February 16, 1955. (Box 1, Folder 21)
    Written from Goldwin Smith Hall, Ithaca NY, in French, with Russian greeting, concerning the film rights for Laughter in the Dark and The Defense. First mention of a long novel that, for "various reasons", VN feels cannot be published in the United States. VN wishes to know whether it will be possible to find a European editor for an English version of this long novel, and suggests that Sylvia Beach might be interested if she is still publishing. Series of questions about possible translators.
  - TLS to Madame D. Ergaz from Vladimir Nabokov, April 17, 1955. (Box 1, Folder 22)
    Written from Goldwin Smith Hall, Ithaca NY, in French, wondering whether Ergaz has anything to say to VN on the subject of "ma LOLITA", and then proceeding onto his continued irritation with Davet's translations.
  - TLS to Madame D. Ergaz from Vladimir Nabokov, May 6, 1955. (Box 1, Folder 23)
    Written from Goldwin Smith Hall, Ithaca NY, in French, regarding ongoing publication and translation issues. VN notes "with pleasure" that Ergaz has begun to work on behalf of Lolita, and writes that although he would be happy to see Lolita translated into French, he would like to see it published in English first.
  - TLS to Madame D. Ergaz from Vladimir Nabokov, May 24, 1955. (Box 1, Folder 24)
    Written from Goldwin Smith Hall, Ithaca NY, in French, expressing satisfaction that Ergaz has found an editor for Lolita, and discussing the logistics of publishing an English and French edition in France, as well as VN's wish to publish the novel under a nom de plume. Short postscript dealing with the title of the French version of Conclusive Evidence. Annotation underlined: "La préface [of Lolita] doit rester telle quelle est."
  - TLS to Madame D. Ergaz from Vladimir Nabokov, June 4, 1955. (Box 1, Folder 25)
    Written from Goldwin Smith Hall, Ithaca NY, in French, expressing great satisfaction at the way "things" are working out, and a readiness to sign the contract (for Lolita) before setting out for the "country." Discussion of publication and translation questions, including the correctness of the French expressions (in the text of Lolita itself). Handwritten postscript, suggesting a possible course of action if Table Rond rejects Lolita.
  - TLS to Madame D. Ergaz from Vladimir Nabokov, July 12, 1955. (Box 1, Folder 26)
    Written from 700 Stewart Avenue, Ithaca NY, in French, confirming that VN has received part of the proofs for Lolita from Maurice Girodias, expressing once more delight over the fast pace of the Lolita publication, briefly asking after some contractual matters and what's happening re: Conclusive Evidence.
  - TLS to Madame D. Ergaz from Vladimir Nabokov, August 19, 1955. (Box 1, Folder 27)
    Writing from 808 Hanshaw Road, Ithaca NY, in French, VN, having just returned from the hospital, is, despite assurances from Ergaz, beginning to feel anxious about Girodias's lack of communication re: the Lolita copyright, date of publication, and the publicity planned. Especially anxious to ensure that payment is made in the US, as the Nabokovs "absolutely need" the money, and it is likely, in any case, that most readers of Lolita will be American or British.
  - TLS to Mademoiselle Marie Schébéko from Vladimir Nabokov, September 21, 1955. (Box 1, Folder 28)
    Writing from Goldwin Smith Hall, Ithaca NY, in French, VN is extremely anxious about Girodias' actions (or lack thereof), describing both G.'s habit of responding neither to phone calls nor letters, evading all questions relating to the matter of copyright, and replying only vaguely to VN's concerns about publicity. VN, skeptical of G.'s claims to be aiming Lolita at the American tourists who, VN feels, will have left France by this time, is beginning to take matters into his own hands (establishing copyright with the Library of Congress, and asking Schébéko for notice of Lolita's publication and the French reviews). Annotated both by VN, and by another hand, perhaps Schébéko or Véra.
  - TLS to Madame D. Ergaz from Vladimir Nabokov, October 6, 1955. (Box 1, Folder 29)
    Written from Goldwin Smith Hall, Ithaca NY, in French, expressing irritation with and a distinct lack of confidence in Girodias, who has taken refuge in silence "in the middle of an important correspondence. I do not like to be treated in this fashion". Continued anxiety over the copyright: "I write for my own pleasure, but I publish in order to live."
  - TLS to Madame D. Ergaz from Vladimir Nabokov, October 8, 1955. (Box 1, Folder 30)
    Written from Goldwin Smith Hall, Ithaca NY, in French, informing Ergaz that he has just received Lolita, "two perfectly elegant little sewn volumes", that he is reassured about the publication of the novel, but continues to worry about the copyright, publicity, and transfer of his payment. Annotated in pencil, in other hand, partly in French, partly in shorthand (Véra?).
  - TLS to Madame D. Ergaz from Vladimir Nabokov, October 8, 1955. (Box 1, Folder 31)
    Written from Goldwin Smith Hall, Ithaca NY, in French, announcing that he has received the money from Girodias, and believes that he will not have any difficult registering copyright in the US except for the fact that he is not receiving any cooperation from Girodias. Thanks Ergaz for her efforts on behalf of his other works ( Conclusive Evidence and The Defense).
  - TLS to Madame D. Ergaz from Vladimir Nabokov, July 10, 1956. (Box 1, Folder 32)
    Addressed from Goldwin Smith Hall, Ithaca NY, but written from Mt. Carmel, in French, expressing satisfaction about the fact that Ergaz has arranged publication rights with "les Danois", and awaiting with "great interest" Ergaz's response to a letter from Véra concerning Conclusive Evidence's date of publication.
  - TLS to Madame D. Ergaz from Vladimir Nabokov, October 22, 1956. (Box 1, Folder 33)
    Written from Goldwin Smith Hall, Ithaca NY, in French, referring to a letter he has sent Ergaz through his wife, explaining that he has forgotten to ask Ergaz for a copy of Priel's translation of Invitation, and will reimburse costs of sending this and other material.
  - TL to Mr. M. Girodias from Vladimir Nabokov, November 25, 1956. (Box 1, Folder 34)
    Written from Goldwin Smith Hall, Ithaca NY, in English, thanking Girodias for his "kind letter" promising not to dispose of the English-language rights of Lolita without VN's permission, and expressing interest in the fact that US customs seems to "have nothing against the book", suggesting that it will not prove difficult to find an American publisher. Urgently entreats G. not to advertize and distribute the novel in the US as G. apparently intends, explaining US copyright laws in terms of the perceived need to protect "American labor against foreign competition." With official sheet from the Library of Congree Copyright Office explaining Interim Copyright, underlined and marked in pencil. Included in Vladimir Nabokov, Selected Letters 1940-1977, pp. 193 - 194.
  - TL to Mr. M. Girodias from Vladimir Nabokov, December 14, 1956. (Box 1, Folder 35)
    With no address (probably written from Goldwin Smith), in English, concerning the publicity campaign for Lolita. VN insists that this is not a novel that "should appeal to the kind of people {G.] euphemistically call 'amateurs'," and refers to a campaign to establish the novel as a "literary achievement of artistic value and lasting importance, and to counteract the unfortunate publicity it received at the start." Reference also to the good reviews that are now appearing in The Partisan Review and The Hudson Review. Included in Vladimir Nabokov, Selected Letters 1940-1977, pp. 196 - 197.
  - TLS to Madame D. Ergaz from Vladimir Nabokov (1), with enclosed copy of TL sent to Mr. M. Girodias (2), March 5, 1957. (Box 1, Folder 36)
    (1) Written from Goldwin Smith Hall, Ithaca NY, in French, explaining that he has refused Girodias' offer to litigate on behalf of Lolita, and then moving on to treat the publication of all his works in French, which he thinks should take place now, at this most favorable time. Complains that his most successful novels, aesthetically speaking, Lolita, Bend Sinister and Invitation, have not been translated yet. (2) Written from Goldwin Smith Hall, Ithaca NY, in English, detailing contract negotiations with American publishing houses, especially their reluctance to take on Lolita because of Girodias' claims as well as fear of "unavoidable court proceedings." In anticipation of an offer from a new publishing house to bring out an American edition, VN proposes that he and G. rewrite their original (and severely flawed) contract. Included in Vladimir Nabokov, Selected Letters 1940-1977, pp. 207 - 208.
  - TLS to Madame D. Ergaz from Vladimir Nabokov, March 24, 1957. (Box 1, Folder 37)
    Written from Goldwin Smith Hall, Ithaca NY, mostly in English save for French salutations, wondering why he and E. have not pulled his books from Table Rond, which appears to be in trouble, and puzzling over the old problem of translation. Refers to Girodias' request that he reconsider his decision to avoid litigation over Lolita, and explains that he will not do so until Girodias agrees to amend their contract. Explains that two American publishers are interested in Lolita, but insist on dealing with VN directly rather than with Olympia. Announces publication of Pnin by Doubleday.
  - TLS to Madame D. Ergaz from Vladimir Nabokov, April 16, 1957. (Box 1, Folder 38)
    Written from Goldwin Smith Hall, Ithaca NY, in French, expressing extreme annoyance with Girodias, particularly since the latter's actions may have a serious negative impact upon VN, and wondering that G. has the nerve to demand a reduction in VN's royalties. Refuses to countenance Eric Kahane (G.'s brother) as French translator for Lolita, since this would confirm to journalists VN's close association with Olympia.
  - TL to Mr. M. Girodias from Vladimir Nabokov, April 17, 1957. (Box 1, Folder 39)
    Written from Goldwin Smith Hall, Ithaca NY, in English, expressing amazement that Girodias is negotiating Lolita with an American publisher, and insisting on Doubleday's right to take or reject Lolita. Hopes that L'affaire Lolita has not been held up by customs, as he has not yet received yet, and concludes by asserting that rather than VN having been the one not to answer G.'s letter of March 12, it is G. who is guilty of not answering.
  - TLS to Madame D. Ergaz from Vladimir Nabokov, April 25, 1957. (Box 1, Folder 40)
    Not addressed, in French. VN is torn between deep gratitude to Olympia for having presented L'affaire Lolita in a brilliant fashion, and impotent rage at the blunders and ridiculous malapropisms of the translation. Includes corrections for the translation errors he finds in his article on Lolita and the novel itself, and exclaims that he has "had it up to here" with these mutilations. VN wishes to accept offers for Lolita from German and Italian publishers, asks for copies of Lolita, and wonders whether review copies have been sent to Harvey Breit, Katharine White, and Philip Rahv. Pencil annotations in Russian and English.
  - TL to Monsieur Gallimard from Vladimir Nabokov, May 7, 1957. (Box 1, Folder 41)
    In French, expressing delight that it is Gallimard that will publish Lolita, and worry about the question of a translator for Lolita. VN suggests Michel Chrestien, but asserts that given the number of allusions in Lolita. to American customs etc. that a non-American or even a non-native English speaker could not be expected to know, VN must be given the translation to check.
  - TL to Mr. M. Girodias from Vladimir Nabokov, May 14, 1957. (Box 1, Folder 42)
    Not addressed, in English. VN outlines reasons why G. cannot possibly want to publish Lolita in the US under his own imprint, or find a second-rate publisher for the novel, including the preponderance of moral institutions in the US prepared to take a text like Lolita to court and the cost of defending such a text in court. VN points out a few of the translation errors in L'affaire Lolita, and concludes that he is "especially annoyed that on p.30 the skit on Eliot does not come out at all". Included in Vladimir Nabokov, Selected Letters 1940-1977, pp. 218 - 219.
  - TLS to Madame D. Ergaz from Vladimir Nabokov, May 14, 1957. (Box 1, Folder 43)
    Not addressed, half in French, half in English, expressing annoyance once more that Girodias not only seems bent on finding a "firm of secondary importance" with whom to place Lolita, but also agrees not to do this in conversation with Ergaz. Reiterates reasons why a second-rate publisher will not do, and outlines a course of action to ensure that his rights (and preferably G.'s) are protected, and that Lolita is published by an appropriate firm able and willing to litigate if necessary. Notes that Ergaz has received Pnin, and suggests that he has found a satisfactory translator for Lolita.
  - TLS to Madame D. Ergaz from Vladimir Nabokov, May 17, 1957. (Box 1, Folder 44)